Guide to the Edward Elsworth Papers, circa 1890-1910
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Edward Elsworth Papers
circa 1890-1910
Elsworth, Edward, 1840-1911
0.2 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
This collection consists of letters written between members of the Vassar College and Poughkeepsie communities and Edward Elsworth, a Vassar College trustee and Mayor of Poughkeepsie, New York.
Biographical Note
Edward Elsworth was a prominent Poughkeepsie lawyer who served as mayor of the city from 1886-1888 and 1890-1892 and was a trustee of Vassar College. Born in New York City on January 6th, 1840, to John and Martha (Van Varick) Elsworth, his parents moved to Poughkeepsie in 1848. Elsworth was educated at Rutger's Grammar School and the Dutchess County Academy, and then graduated from the State and National Law School in Poughkeepsie graduated in 1858. After graduating, he was admitted to the bar in 1861 and became managing clerk for Bernard Roelker in New York City. He practiced law for several years in Dutchess and Rockland counties, and was a trustee of many local institutions, including Poughkeepsie Savings Bank, Fallkill National Bank, and Vassar Brothers' Institute. He was elected a trustee of Vassar College in 1892 and also served as treasurer of the college for a decade, succeeding Willard L. Dean in 1899. He died in 1911, at the age of 71.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of letters written between members of the Vassar College and Poughkeepsie communities and Edward Elsworth, a Vassar College trustee and Mayor of Poughkeepsie, New York. In particular, fourteen letters from Vassar College President, James Monroe Taylor, are included, as well as eight letters from Elsworth to Taylor.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Vassar College Board of Trustees Records
Vassar College Office of the Treasurer Records
Subject Headings
Names:
Backus, Helen H. (Helen Hiscock), -1906; Dean, Willard L., -1898; Taylor, James Monroe, 1848-1916; Thompson, Frederick Ferris, 1836-1899
Document Types:
Correspondence
VCL Categories:
Vassar College Trustees
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, January 2026.
Acquisition Information
Letters to Edward Elsworth were purchased in two parts, November 2025. [M2026-002, M2026-003]
Container List
- Letters from Backus, Helen Hiscock to Elsworth, Edward, 1899 Feb 16; [2 letters] (Folder 1)
- Letter from Dean, Willard L. to Elsworth, Edward, 1893 Nov 9 (Folder 2)
- Letter from Elsworth, Edward to ["Mr. Bossitir?"], 1895 Oct 16 (Folder 3)
- Letter from Elsworth, Edward to Drennan, Manuel J., circa 1894 (Folder 3)
- Letter from Elsworth, Edward to Noyes, Albert F., 1895 Apr 1 (Folder 3)
- Letter from Elsworth, Edward to [Salmon, Lucy Maynard?], 1906 Mar 13 (Folder 3)
- Letter from Elsworth, Edward to Taylor, James Monroe, [1892?] Jul 4 (Folder 4)
- Letters from Elsworth, Edward to Taylor, James Monroe, 1894; [4 letters] (Folder 4)
- Letters from Elsworth, Edward to Taylor, James Monroe, 1910 Jan-Jun; [3 letters] (Folder 5)
- Letter from Elsworth, Edward to "Miss Wright,", 1905 Jul 1 (Folder 3)
- Letter from Loomis, Mabel Ruth to Elsworth, Edward, circa 1890s (Folder 6)
- Letter from Mills, Herbert Elmer to Elsworth, Edward, 1893 Apr 13 (Folder 7)
- Letter from Noyes, Albert F. to Elsworth, Edward, 1895 Jun 20 (Folder 8)
- Letters from Taylor, James Monroe to Elsworth, Edward, 1893 Mar; [2 letters] (Folder 9)
- Letters from Taylor, James Monroe to Elsworth, Edward, 1894; [6 letters] (Folder 10)
- Letters from Taylor, James Monroe to Elsworth, Edward, 1895; [5 letters] (Folder 11)
- Letter from Taylor, James Monroe to Elsworth, Edward, 1899 Jan 25 (Folder 12)
- Letter from Thompson, Frederick Ferris to Taylor, James Monroe, 1895 Jul 10 (Folder 13)
- Letter from Thompson, Mary Clark to Elsworth, Edward, 1899 Feb 10 (Folder 14)